benchmarking so you've just written some
code and you want to see how fast it
actually runs because you're working on
a session that's rather performance
critical or you're testing out this new
kind of technique that you've just
learned about but you want to compare
the performance back through the way
that you used to do it in the past and
see which way is faster how how do you
do that in C++ so unfortunately there's
no right answer really to benchmarking
because there's so many different ways
to do it and everyone has their own kind
of way of actually measuring performance
because it's such a touchy subject you
know if you do it in the wrong way then
maybe the fact that you're measuring the
performance itself is gonna add overhead
to it some people like to rely on
third-party profiling tools some people
like to actually instrument their code
and have things like timers to them some
people like to just run their program
and just enclose the whole program in
kind of a climber and just write a
specific program for testing what what
it is that they want to test there's
just so many different ways that you can
actually do this so what's the right way
well I of course don't have a right way
but I have the way that I do it and
that's what I want to share with you
guys today we're gonna talk about how we
can actually measure the performance of
C++ code I just want to point out as
well that the topic of benchmarking is
much more than the tools that you use to
actually benchmark your code if you're
trying to measure performance of a piece
of suppose cost code that itself
requires you to actually do that
quote-unquote properly there's many
different ways to do that as well I
don't really want to get into them in
this video but I think what I will do is
make a video and I'll link it up there
when it's made of just like a bunch of
tips basically that I have for just
ensuring that the performance that you'd
like when you actually run your program
and you're measuring the performance
you're actually doing it in a way that
the results are going to be somewhat
meaningful because there's just so many
things to consider when you're actually
kind of preparing a code for
benchmarking so the first thing I do is
write some code that we actually want to
test so I'm going to do something very
simple I wanna have this value and then
I'm gonna have a for loop which just
increments the value like you know a lot
of times let's just say like a million
times so this is gonna be value plus
equals we'll just increment it by two
and then finally what I'll do is
actually print that value into the
console I'll stick a breakpoint here and
this is a visual
studio this is kind of a windows only
function but all its going to do is
break the compiler here so that I don't
have to like insert some code here and
then put a breakpoint myself so if we
run that what we should get is just a
little program that will print the value
basically two times that so here it is
right there's about you fantastic so now
that we've got that we want to actually
analyze how fast our code is so the way
that I like to do this is basically to
create a simple kind of scoped based
time and now I do have a video about
timing in C++ which you can also check
out and this is going to be basically
something of the sort
so we're going to make a class up here
called timer and usually of course that
keeps in some sort of library we're
gonna rely on foreign oil for this the
constructor is going to actually start
the timer so what we'll do is we'll keep
track of the time point that we get from
the high resolution clock so this piece
of code gets the current time as a
specific time point you can see it's an
STD chrono time point so what we're
gonna do is store that in a private
member variables so STD chrono time
point and it's going to be an STD high
resolution clock we'll call this house
start time point and that's what we're
assigning into our start time point now
we're going to write a stop function but
this will be automatically called in the
destructor like this because I want this
to be scope base which basically means
that it's tied to the lifetime of the
object so in other words when this
object gets created we start the timer
when the object gets destroyed we stop
the timer so this is basically our a III
or resource acquisition is
initialization so here we have a little
bit more work in the stop method we'll
just do the order here for a lot of
these things because they have very long
types so we'll have our end time point
and the end time point will just be
again the current time so when we start
a timer we take note of the current time
of course and when we sell the time and
we take note of the current time
so now we'll work out what the start
time actually is as an actual value so
what this will be what we'll need to do
here it's just time point past this to
our the units that we want to use which
in this case because I want to be fairly
precise will use microseconds but you
can also use millisecond
that's totally fine depends on what
you're measuring a lot of the times when
you're measuring something it might be
below one millisecond and if it's below
one millisecond and you're measuring in
milliseconds you look like it's just
useless data so microseconds is just a
way for us to actually get some
meaningful data if it's really that fun
so we'll get a start time point here
we'll use our start time point - that's
what we're casting me in two
microseconds this will basically get us
the time since like the beginning of
time and we'll get the count off of that
okay so that's what we end up with it's
a fairly long little function here
because we need to cast into the right
time and then convert into into this
time and then actually get the count
which will kind of give us the
microsecond count of the start time okay
fantastic and this will this I believe
returns a long long yes so that's what
they water what kind of B it's a long
long and then we'll do the same thing
for the end but instead of doing start
time point we of course do the same to
that end time point and that is where we
stop okay so now we just need to
calculate the duration so auto duration
equals and minus start it's that simple
and of course we should call this and or
not stop okay so now if we wanted to for
example calculate the milliseconds
because it's in microseconds all we need
to do is just multiply duration by 0.001
and that will just give us the
microseconds but in milliseconds with
you know decimal points that we can
actually see how many milliseconds that
was so now it's kind of up to you what
you do with this data now because this
is kind of scope based it will just get
destroyed so what you need to do if you
want to kind of do anything here and
what I usually end up doing is actually
outputting this data from this stop
function into some kind of tracker which
actually keeps track of what has been
measured and what the actual results
have been but that's a very large system
that actually outputs like all the data
as a file and does a bunch of things so
that you can actually view it in
separate tools and see how long
everything in your program took me if
you like making a game you'll see how
long each frame took and what the
functions in the frames were that we're
expensive and that's like a whole system
and that's definitely gonna be saved for
another video but for now what we're
going to do is just output duration so
we'll say
Oh we'll do fee for this really is just
awkward duration so that have been
microseconds so we can just write like
us I don't have that micro simple handle
candy and then we'll do the milliseconds
as well and do milliseconds in fact
because this is like this I might just
do encase instead
so we'll do ms and then milliseconds
like that so let's do it all in one line
so 20 microseconds it is that's how many
milliseconds it is okay cool
so that's it right so what we should be
able to do is now basically if we want
to time something like this we can just
wrap this whole part that we want to
time into a time up like this right now
what I'll do with the value is I'll move
the value up here so that we can still
access it in our print function but
that's it we just stick that block of
code where we want the time to start and
it will last with the duration of this
entire scope so now let's hit f5 and see
what value we get out of our timer so
there's our break point that we hit and
you can see that this took three point
six nine milliseconds cool now I just
want to mention here that it's really
important to make sure that what you're
supposedly measuring is actually the
code that gets compiled because they
both cost compiler obviously can
optimize code and strip certain code out
and change your code entirely for
example we've written this wonderful
function here and we're running in debug
mode so what what I'll do is I'll just
kind of put a breakpoint here and I'll
right-click somewhere and hit go to
disassembly now this is this is the
sweet stuff right this is the actual
assembly code that your compiler has
compiled your C++ code into and then
from that machine code it's been kind of
decompiled back into assembly code so
that we can actually see the
instructions that our CPU is executing
so if we take a look at what's happening
here we have this for loop that's not
that interesting but then let's say this
is our value so what we're doing here is
what we're really timing right bar from
like the overhead from say the for loop
is what we're trying to work out how
long it takes to add one number to
another number right so that our
operation is right over here right so
what we do for this code is we move this
value variable that's it right here into
the EAX register we add 2 to that EAX
register
that's what does the increment and then
we move
the value from that EAX register back
into the actual value variable and then
we jump to like a different part in our
code so this actual edition you can see
is happening it's right over here we can
see it in the assembly code which means
our CPU is actually doing it now watch
what happens if I switch my
configuration to release and hit f5 and
now check this out so it looks like
there's a whole lot less code and
specifically if we take a look at this I
mean well there's no add instruction
anywhere here is there no not at all
it looks like what's actually happening
is we're calling this function here
which is that operator which is our
print function and before we do that we
push a variable on to the stack and that
value you look at it one e eight four
eight is zero if we just open a
programmer calculator here and see that
value is two million in decimal so
what's actually happened is the compiler
has looked at this code and realized
that this does not need to be computed
at run time and is optimized it into
just figuring this out at compile time
and all we're doing now is printing the
value two million we're not doing any
kind of increment at all so my point is
that this kind of the results of this
from our timer they're gonna be
completely useless because we're not
measuring out anymore we're basically
measuring how long it takes to print
something in fact not even that because
that timer scope does not include the
printing function so whatever you're
actually trying to benchmark something
make sure that you're actually doing the
work that needs to be done you're not
just kind of measuring absolutely
nothing taking place because the
compiler can actually quite aggressively
change your code like you can see here
I'm gonna give you guys one last example
what I'm gonna do is measure the
performance of a shared pointer versus a
unique point of now this is kind of a
hot topic to hear about all the time do
we have any kind of overhead from using
smart pointers should we use them what
we'll actually do here is we'll test it
out so I'll include array because I'm
gonna do that and what I'm gonna do is
just create a whole bunch of pointers so
I prayed a little class just to test out
it'll be a vector to class we'll just
have flow to exploit Y and then what
I'll do is I'll create an array of
shared pointer this will be a vector two
and we'll create 1000 of them so just
just a thousand this isn't even going to
be that kind of big ok so we have all of
our shared pointers here and then what
I'll do is inside a for loop which
through every element in that array
we'll actually have to initialize those
pointers that will create them so we'll
say shared pointers I equals s TV makes
share this is another little thing that
we can test by the way we have this make
shared function which we've heard is
supposedly good but we should measure
the performance of this versus if we
just used if we didn't use make sure if
we just kind of just use new to go to
actually create the vector two and then
sort it inside a inside of SharePoint o
so we'll put a timer here we don't
really want to time the making of the
array so we'll just put the timer here
just closer to our actual code that we
care about and then what I'll do is I'll
copy this code I'll paste it here but
instead of make shared what I'm gonna do
is actually change this to be STD shared
pointer vector two and I'll just do new
vector two just like that okay so now
this is kind of the second scenario and
finally what I'll do is I'll just use a
unique pointer instead so this will be
make unique and I can get rid of this
and obviously change this to be a unique
pointer all right that was pretty good
one thing one last thing that I'll do
just so that we're a little bit more
clear is I'll just label this basically
so we'll have make shared we will have
I'll call this new shared and I'll call
this make unique okay so we have three
different tests here of course this
actual printing is not getting timed
because it's outside the time scope
let's hit at five and see what we get
okay and as you can see some were
expected we have our shared pointers
taking more time than our unique
pointers but wait a minute
look at this make shared actually seems
to be taking more time than new shed and
I can of course we run this program and
see if we get different results okay so
now make sure it looks like it might be
faster let's run this again now new shed
is faster right so these two seem to be
about on top of each other but there's
one vital thing that we're doing here
we're actually profiling this in debug
mode and that's not particularly great
for measuring performance because it
does a whole lot of extra safety stuff
which take time so we'll switch our
configuration to release and then
on our code now you can see we have this
whole different ballgame apart from
being a lot faster in release mode a lot
faster we can also see that make shed is
significantly faster than new shed and
if we try and run this again you'll see
that we get fairly consistent results of
make sure being faster than new shed so
always make sure that you profile code
that is actually meaningful in a release
because you're not gonna be shipping
code in debug anyway release will strip
away any kind of extra fluff that might
be done and you can see that here we get
kind of consistent results of what we
would actually expect now for this
example of shared pointers well I mean
we're not even like accessing the data
we're not even like sharing the data
with other shed pointers or anything on
that is pretty much it not a very good
test but my point is that is how the
timing works and that's how we can
benchmark our C++ code I hope you guys
enjoyed this video if you did you can
hit the like button you can also help
support the series on patreon.com
forward slash the channel thank you so
much to everyone who helped support this
channel as I mentioned I do want to make
that follow-up video where I talk about
how to actually measure this stuff
properly there's so many little things
that you need to know to make sure that
the data the results you're actually
getting from this are actually
meaningful and not just fake but until
then I'll see you next time goodbye
[Music]